[Music]
researchers who accept grants from the
cocacola company call physical
inactivity the greatest public health
problem of the 21st century actually
physical inactivity ranks down at number
10 for risk factors for death in the
United States and number 11 for risk
factors for disability and globally in
terms of years of healthy life lost
inactivity doesn't even break into the
top 20
as we've learned diet is our greatest
killer followed by smoking a media
analysis found hundreds of news articles
claiming that prolonged daily sitting is
as bad or even worse than smoking this
is decidedly not the case smoking is
expected to cause a billion deaths this
Century tobacco is responsible for up to
more than 10 times greater mortality
risk comparing the heaviest smokers
versus is the heaviest
sitters what role does physical activity
play in longevity in terms of combating
the H marks of Aging aerobic exercise
can induce autophagy lower inflammation
decrease DNA damage facilitate DNA
repair a meta analysis of cohort studies
of middle-aged and older individuals
with follow-ups as long as 20 years
found that exercising adults were more
likely to age successfully than
sedentary individuals population Studies
have found out correlation between
regular aerobic exercise and decreased
risk of at least 35 different diseases
but what have Interventional trials
proven in terms of cause and effect
randomized control Trials of older
adults have demonstrated the physical
activity can improve muscle mass and
strength
balance and
Mobility decrease the risk of
Falls and potential fr cures while
helping to minimize bone loss exercise
may also improve cognition enhance mood
successfully treat depression as well as
the prescription of the anti-depressant
drug Zoloft improve erectile function in
men and generally improve quality of
life the evidence supporting the overall
health benefits of physical activity are
overwhelming exercise is
medicine artery stiffness is recognized
as a barometer of Aging supporting the
17th century Axiom from the English
hypocrates that man is as old as his
arteries normally large arteries in the
body expand and recoil with every
heartbeat that's the pulse you feel in
your wrist this helps cushion the
pressure waves to prevent damage to Tiny
sensitive blood vessels and organs like
your brain and kidneys thankfully not
all age related stiffening is inevitable
endurance trained men and women have
artery elasticity closer to that of
younger sedentary individuals a status
that can be achieved after daily brisk
walks or jogging for just 3 months this
may help explain why those who exercise
appear to live so much longer a single
exercise session can improve insulin
sensitivity for up to 17 hours exercise
is such powerful medicine that
researchers at Stanford and London
School found that exercise may work as
well as drugs for patients with coronary
heart disease heart failure and
pre-diabetes and even better than some
medications for stroke they suggested
that drug companies should perhaps be
required to compare any new chronic
disease drugs head-to-head against
exercise as patients deserve to
understand the relative impact that
physical activity might have on their
condition exercise has been described as
the only intervention that has shown a
remarkable efficacy for increasing mean
and maximum lifespans in humans but is
that true can we exercise power over our
lifespan is it really survival of the
fittest that's exactly what I'll
explore next
[Music]